David Leeming Collection of James Baldwin Research
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
David Leeming Collection of James Baldwin Research
1950-2002
JWJ MSS 172
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.63
9 boxes
Leeming, David Adams, 1937-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 1-8 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Arranged into four series: I. Audiocassettes, II. Videocassettes, III. Photographs, IV. Other Papers.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain audiocassettes, videocassettes, photographs, correspondence, and printed material related to David Leeming's biography of James Baldwin, James Baldwin: A Biography. The audiocassettes contain interviews with various family, friends, and colleagues of James Baldwin and his close friend and mentor, Beauford Delaney. The videocassettes contain television programs and an anthology of films on Baldwin. The photographs depict portraits of Baldwin and snapshots of Baldwin alone and with friends in his Saint-Paul-de-Vence residence and at other locations. Other Papers includes correspondence regarding Leeming's research and permissions for his biography on Baldwin, James Baldwin's autograph signature, and two published books by Leeming.
Biographical / Historical
David Leeming, born February 26, 1937 in Peekskill, New York. Leeming is professor emeritus of English and comparative literature at the University of Connecticut. He wrote James Baldwin: A Biography and Amazing Grace: A Life of Beauford Delaney.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David Leeming on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, October 2016.
American literature -- United States -- Archives; Authors, American -- United States -- Archives; Audiocassettes -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Sound recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Video recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Biographers -- United States -- 20th Century; Baldwin, James, 1924-1987; Delaney, Beauford, 1901-1979; Leeming, David Adams, 1937-
- Audiocassettes, 1968–1999; I; 4
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 1-4 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by individual interviewed by David Leeming and audiocassette labels assigned by Leeming. The groupings Friends of James Baldwin in Turkey and Friends of Beauford Delaney were established by Leeming.
  - Baldwin, David, undated; 1; 01:22:10; Background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886248)
  - Baldwin, David, 1989 January; 1; 01:26:45 (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886230)
  - "Baldwin/ML King, 'Sickness of America'", 1968 March 16; 1; 01:23:06; The program is distorted at times. Audio cuts in and out from approximately 00:38:29 until the end of the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886255)
  - Baldwin, James. Interview in France, 1983 May 18; 1; 01:04:37; Background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886263)
  - Baldwin, James. Interview in France, 1985 June 24; 1; 01:15:55; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886271)
  - Belli, Bill (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 01:33:03; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886289)
  - Belli, Bill (2 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 01:33:02; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886297)
  - Belli, Bill 3 and Brock Peters 1, undated; 1; 01:17:14; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. There are drop outs in the sound at about 00:30:00. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886305)
  - "Bits and Pieces", undated; 1; 01:23:07; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. Drop outs in audio can be heard at about 00:47:00 and again near the end of the recording. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886313)
  - Blumenau, Mary Keen, undated; 1; 01:08:02; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886321)
  - Brown, Cecil, 1989 May; 1; 01:32:42; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886339)
  - Burch, Claire. Berkeley, 1989 February; 1; 01:20:35; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886347)
  - Cezzar, Engin (1 of 2), undated; 1; 00:07:22; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886354)
  - Cezzar, Engin (2 of 2), undated; 1; 01:32:37; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886362)
  - Cezzar, Engin and Yasar Kemal, undated; 1; 00:47:22; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886370)
  - Champion, Ernest, 1991 October; 1; 01:02:35; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. There are drop outs in audio at about 00:47:00. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886388)
  - Christian, Barbara. Berkeley, 1989 February; 1; 00:27:29; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886396)
  - Crawford, Marc, undated; 1; 01:23:10; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886404)
  - Dallas, Walter, 1991 July; 1; 01:15:10; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886412)
  - Davis, [Angela?] and Bill Styron debate with Baldwin as moderator, 1968 May; 1; 01:30:00; Static and a high amount of hum can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886420)
  - Democracy Now! On James Baldwin, 1999 August 2; 1; 00:51:31; Static and a high amount of buzz can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Item barcode 39002104886438)
  - Early, Robert, undated; 1; 01:02:04; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886446)
  - Fontaine, Dick, undated; 1; 01:11:23 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886453)
  - Friends of James Baldwin in Turkey
    - Pakay, Sedat, undated; 1; 00:53:45; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886461)
    - Polliar, Nidra, undated; 1; 00:33:35; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886479)
    - Ofluoglu, Feliz, 1998 June 27; 1; 01:02:22; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886487)
    - "Zeynep Oral", 1988 June 25; 1; 00:52:13; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886495)
  - Friends of Beauford Delaney
    - "Clark, Genfry, [Blockburn?]", 1994 October 16; 1; 01:30:32; The program is distorted at times. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886503)
    - "Delaney sisters, Imogen, [Oqust?]", undated; 1; 01:35:29 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886511)
    - Boggs, Charley, undated; 1; 01:35:07 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886529)
    - "Delaneys/[Oqust] and Imogen", 1995 October 24; 1; 01:35:12; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886537)
    - Gibson, Richard (1 of 2), undated; 1; 00:57:27; The program is distorted at times. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886545)
    - Gibson, Richard (2 of 2), 1995 January 19; 1; 01:34:12; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886552)
    - "Museum of City of New York, opening of Canada Lee Archive", undated; 1; 01:07:13 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886560)
    - "Talking about Beauford Delaney, Boggs/Brct", 1991 January 10; 1; 01:03:19; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886578)
      Scope and Contents
      Taped in the Atelier Charles Biggs 5, Cite Falguiere with T'Ang, Phillipe Briet, Charles Boggs. Note for David Leeming: I met T'Ang (Hay Wen) the Chinese Painter, in Paris in 1951. We were friends, then, for 40 years. And I introduced him to Beauford early on. T'Ang died of AIDS about 8 months after this tape was made, he died in hospital 26 September 1991. He was 60 years old. - Charles Boggs
    - "Masurovsky", 1995 May; 1; 00:55:33; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886586)
    - "Boggs, Charley/[Naughton]/DL, undated; 1; 01:02:25 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886594)
    - Boggs, Charley (1 of 2), undated; 1; 01:19:12; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886602)
    - Boggs, Charley (2 of 2), undated; 1; 00:56:58; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886610)
    - Boggs, Charley/Nimmo/DL", undated; 1; 01:35:06 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886628)
    - "Michelle Le Gros, Judith Bledsoe", undated; 1; 01:32:44; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886636)
    - Speyer, Darthea, undated; 1; 00:53:56; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002104886644)
    - "Jennings/Overstreet", undated; 1; 01:33:44; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886651)
    - "Jennings/Overstreet", undated; 1; 01:10:12; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886669)
    - "Canada Lee, Readings and Dramatic Presentations", undated; 1; 00:49:06; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886677)
    - "Conversation with Joe Delaney", 1989 December 25; 1; 00:40:59; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886685)
    - "Jim and Bunny LeGros on BD", undated; 1; 00:56:28; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886693)
    - "Gentry, Herb; Clark[e], Blockburn", undated; 1; 01:31:51; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886701)
    - West, Dorothy, undated; 1; 00:12:13; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886719)
    - Long, Richard on Beauford Delaney, September 23; 1; 00:10:30; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886727)
  - Gold, Herbert, undated; 1; 01:22:52; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886735)
  - Hassell, Bernard (1 of 2), 1984 Summer; 1; 00:58:51; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886743)
  - Hassell, Bernard (2 of 2), 1988 June; 1; 00:47:21; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. Drop outs in audio can be heard at the beginning of the tape and at about 00:47:00. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886750)
  - "Hassell, Bernard and then Lucien Happersberger and Bernard and Valerie", 1988 June; 1; 01:22:37; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886768)
    Includes fragments of interviews with Baldwin's longtime partner Lucien Happersberger with comments from Baldwin's housekeeper in France, Valerie Sordello.
  - Happersberger, Lucien, 1988 June 16; 1; 01:12:50; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886776)
  - Hoetis, Themistocles, undated; 1; 01:02:40; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. The audio drops out at the beginning of the tape and at about 00:46:30 in. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886784)
  - Levister, [Lorie?], 1991 March 2; 1; 01:07:08; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886792)
  - Long, Richard, 1991 April 5; 1; 01:09:33; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886800)
  - "Malcolm Debates" four scholars, 1961 April 23; 1; 00:57:31; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is very distorted. The program becomes unintelligible over time. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886818)
  - Miller, Orilla "Bill". Miller's Memorial, undated; 1; 01:41:20; The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886826)
  - Miller, Orilla "Bill". Ojai, 1989 February 20; 1; 01:31:47; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886834)
  - Moses, David, 1984 February 21; 1; 01:32:36; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886842)
  - Nelson, Leonard, 1989 February 22; 1; 01:04:39; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 3, Item barcode 39002104886859)
  - Ove, Horace, 1990 February 18; 1; 00:42:38; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. The tape speed gets faster from about 00:21:00 until the end of the recording. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886867)
  - Richards, Lloyd, 1991 July 5; 1; 00:23:51; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886875)
  - Scheinfeld, Gary, 1991; 1; 01:20:11; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886883)
  - Silberman, Jim, 1991 January 15; 1; 01:01:29; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886891)
    Interview with James Baldwin
  - Sordello, Valerie, 1988 June 16; 1; 00:09:53; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. There are drop outs in the audio at the beginning of the recording. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886909)
  - Trevelyan, Raleigh, 1988 June; 1; 01:34:17; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886917)
  - Williams, Connie, 1991 August; 1; 01:12:01; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886925)
  - "Words of a Native Son", 1963 February 21; 1; 01:03:39; Static as well as clicks and pops are heard on the tape. There is also a high amount of hum heard throughout the first 32 minutes of the recording. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886933)
  - "[illegible]", undated; 1; 01:33:03; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 4, Item barcode 39002104886941)
- Videocassettes, 2002, undated; II
  Boxes 5-8 (videocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - The James Baldwin Anthology, A Claire Bruch Film, undated; 1 (Box 5)
  - A&E Biography, Witness: James Baldwin, undated; 1 (Box 6)
    This is a commercial videocassette. It has not been digitized.
  - "James Baldwin", undated; 1 (Box 7)
  - Writings of James Baldwin, 2002 June 16; 1 (Box 8)
- Photographs, 1950-1987, undated; III; 1
  - Transparency of Beauford Delaney's portrait of David Leeming, undated (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Saint-Paul-de-Vence house, photo by Leeming, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Saint-Paul-de-Vence, undated (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Baldwin cooking in Istanbul, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Baldwin and Bernard Hassel in Saint-Paul-de-Vence at the "welcome table", 1980s (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Lucien Happersberger in France, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Baldwin in last week of life, photo by Leeming, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Black and white and color photograph of last dinner at table in Saint-Paul-de-Vence with Baldwin, photo by Leeming, undated (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - James and David Baldwin in Russia, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Baldwin in Istanbul, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Baldwin at Leeming house in Connecticut, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Baldwin's final bedroom in Saint-Paul-de-Vence, Leeming photo, undated (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Baldwin's living room in Saint-Paul-de-Vence, Leeming photo, undated (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Valerie Sardello, Baldwin's housekeeper in Saint-Paul-de-Vence, photograph by Leeming, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Baldwin, undated (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Baldwin and unidentified individual, undated (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Four portraits of Baldwin by Jerry Bauer, Rome, undated (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Two portraits of Baldwin by Juno Gemes, 1979, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - One portrait of Baldwin by P. Shiras in Istanbul, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Mary Painter in France, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 92)
- Other Papers, 1977-1998, undated; IV; 7
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from Berdis Emma Jones Baldwin to David Leeming regarding Bill Weatherby's search for Baldwin's biological father, undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Letters of permission from James and David Baldwin and Bernard Hassell regarding Leeming's James Baldwin: A Biography with two birthday cards to Leeming, 1977–1990 (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Photocopies of 1963-1965 letters to Leeming from James Baldwin, undated (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Photocopies of 1966 and 1969 correspondence between Kay Boyle and James Baldwin, undated (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - James Baldwin autograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Printed Material
    - Leeming, David. James Baldwin: A Biography. 1994, First Arcade Edition 2015, New York (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Leeming, David. Amazing Grace, Oxford University Press, 1998, New York (Box 9, Folder 99)